[Music]
Hi, welcome to Busy Central Lunch
Edition 2025 release wave 2. Today I
will explain you what is new in
sustainability related to one compliance
topic CBM and EPR reporting.
Before we jumping into details, first I
want to explain if you are new in this
topic what CBM and EPR are. So CBM is
carbon border adjustment mechanism.
It exists to prevent our carbon leakage.
Uh this is in European Union. So this is
specific tool in our applies to carbon
price on import certain good from
outside of European Union. So it
prevents to import from another
countries and to decrease artificially
to decrease carbon in uh European Union
countries. On the other side, EPR is
extended producer responsibility. So
this is new environmental policy that
approach to hold producer accountability
for entire life cycle of products. So
this is something what we need to track
inside the business center through
entire life cycle and it includes
collection and recycling disposal
packaging and other waste. So this is
not applicable for all items but for
many of them. So let's look business
values about that why we deliver uh this
functionality in the first place. So
with that uh regulatory alignment it
made much easier. So you will have
everything by design inside the B
central. You can have all not all but
many of new European Union regulations
as this time as the CBMPR inside the
system. Then it will definitely reduce
the risk environmental impact. So not
not only about compliance uh it will
promote echco-friendly practices. So
from two different reasons and on the
end it improve operational efficiency
because now you can be focused what you
really need to do. You do not need to
focus to reporting. If you properly set
up your system, system will track and
when you need to report CBM, EPR, you
can do it relatively easily.
How we made it? You can find another
session about excise taxes. Why I say
that in a framework we are using a
foundation we are using excise taxes new
framework. So this is new framework we
delivered and first two functionalities
because framework is just a framework.
We do not have specific calculation in
the framework but first two calculation
we introduced were uh CBM and EPR based
on a set some set of specific rules for
calculations
and before we start I want to show you
prerequisites what you need to set up
because definitely it requires some
setup so you can track all this
information on CBAM
you need to set up first setup uh carbon
pricing table new table new page you
will find. So you must set up uh carbo
pricing and then you need to set up your
items. Each of items you will see I will
show you what you need to set up. So
this is important. On other side EPR is
little bit different. So first we have
EPR materials. This is just a list of
all materials required to be tracked in
a EPR based on EPR requirements. And
then using these EPR materials you will
use item material composition. This is
the page very similar with the
production bill material. In general for
each of items you need to explain uh
what of EPR materials will be used for
producing and of course on the end you
need to set up items to use all these
things. So where it apply CBM applies to
purchase documents and on other side EPR
applies to sales documents. So let's
look what is inside. Let's start with
the CBM setup and calculation.
Okay, as I said, first we have carbon
pricing table.
You need to set up few things there. So
you need to choose for each of
countries. You need to set up uh
starting and ending date. Actually you
need to set up starting date. It doesn't
mean that you need immediately ending
date. But if carbon price is changing,
you need to set up ending date and then
to create new starting and ending date
for next period. So then you need to set
up unit of measure how you will
calculate and what will be the price for
uh carbon carbon price. For example,
this is kilogram. What will be price for
this 1 kilogram in a as a carbo price
and one more thing you need to say what
is the threshold because it will not
apply for all values. for example
purchases really small uh num small
amounts you are not you are not supposed
to report CBM so you need to set up your
threshold
uh okay you have rounder policy so you
can uh choose if this is nearest or how
you want to set up and again just not to
forget this is per country you can use
for all countries if you have the same
carbon price for all countries so you do
not set up specific countries but again
it will be the best option to set up
because in this moment and system can
track for where you purchased. So this
is the best option and even it can help
because sometimes you can have different
price car prices from different
countries. Okay, this is first you need
to check it, you need to set up sorry
and then you need to switch to items.
You need to open one item and when you
open this item
let's switch to sustainability fast tab
and what you need you you must have
there on the first place you need to
have set up sustainability account and
then you need to have a minimum carbon
emissions default carbon emission for
this item. So you can have three
different emissions there. You can track
all of them. You can calculate what your
carbon equivalent emission is but
minimum you need to have carbon. Then
you need to switch um to setup for CBAM.
So you just need to check what is your
emission verify place. If this is for
vendor certify or some other uh resource
and then when you have chose for example
I have vendor then you need to choose to
mark if emission is verified or not and
if this is CBM compliant or not. So only
CBM compliant items will be used for
calculation and it is important
information if emission is verified or
not. So uh about uh emission information
you can enter uh direct an item or when
you make purchase system will
automatically collect and uh enter into
carbon equivalent value. So you can use
both of these options. So now let's
switch to purchase invoice
and as I already have vendor so I just
need to enter some uh lines. So I have
four lines for different items uh in my
uh purchase invoice. And what is
important you need to go on the right
side little bit and you will find this
information if this is verified CBN
compliant. So I have marked for all
these items. So all good. What I need to
do I just need to post. When I post
document okay I will confirm
everything is good. So now I can switch
to my new excise journal. going there
you need to choose what is your batch.
In a batch you need to have CBM uh as a
excise type. So if you already have this
you just need to calculate and then
you will be asked do you want to
calculate journal lines? Of course if I
say yes you will get some lines.
Okay I will not read all lines you have
there. You will find that this is
calculated based on purchase invoice.
What is invoice number? who is a vendor,
if this is verified, if this is CBM uh
compliant. So all this information about
items about total emissions. So all
these informations are here. So you will
find even country as a origin country
and um all other information already
calculated if this is uh over the
threshold if not it will not be
calculated here. Now I just wanted to uh
explain about country of region. So
system will first uh look if there is
country of a region of item. If there is
country of a region on item card system
will use this one. If not then system
will use from vendor uh vendor country
as a country of region. So then we just
need to register and when we register we
can go to uh excise taxes uh transaction
logs and then you can find all these new
entries created
what we have all of them are marked as a
excess tax as a CBM as a purchase. So
you can go there and find all these
carbon prices calculated. So everything
is there. So from there this is easily
to be ex exported and to use for
reporting. So now let's switch to EPR
setup and calculation.
We will start with the EPR materials. As
I said this is simple table.
So you just need to create some names.
For example you have plastic, metal so
on. So then you can say what is uh unit
of measure then EPR fees calculated and
verify date. So that's it. This is just
simplified table. Nothing special. Then
we will switch to the item because you
need to create composition but we can do
it from item. Let's open one item. Again
we will go to the sustainability fast
tab and then we have EPR category. We
need to choose what is your EPR
category. As I said, it doesn't apply to
all item types. If this is packaging or
electronics, so it depends what is
about. But if your item is one of them,
you need to choose which one. Okay, I'll
choose for example packaging here. Now,
we need to enter material composition
number. As you can see, I do not have
currently any material composition in my
system. So, I can just choose new one to
create. And then I will populate
information header. As you can see
material composition page is almost the
same as a bill of material. So in
general it is very similar because you
have information header for uh about
item you are creating this information
and then on the lines you will have all
your EPR materials you're using for this
composition. So once when we have
created and choose unit of measure we
have as a default on this item we need
to enter information into lines. So you
can choose one of your um materials EPR
materials if you have your system. I
enter three uh different EPR materials
and then you can configure what is the
weight for each of them related to this
one unit of measure. In our case unit of
measure for main item is pieces. So how
many kilograms or aluminum or whatever
we have for one piece of this item. Then
all other information are already
calculated. But if you extend this page,
you can find there are few more
information there. Calculation fee,
sorting fee, some other fees. So you
have an option to add these other fees
if they're required. So this is on you.
This is a setup. So EPR fee is by
default. Others fees are something you
can if you need to add.
Okay. Once when you complete, what do
you need to do? You need to change the
status of your material composition from
new to certify again very similar and
very familiar with bill of materials and
just confirm. Okay. So now we have set
it up and then you can find that we have
total EPR weight EPR per unit. So
everything is already calculated from
our composition page. Okay. One more
thing you need to configure end of life
disposal information. So this is pure
textual information. You have 50
characters. This is something you need
to report. So you need to have this
information not mandatory. So if you
need to report, you can add for each of
items here.
So what else? Now when we have all of
these configured, we will switch into
the sales invoice. This time is a if you
remember CBM is for purchase, EPR is for
sales. And as we have some items you can
find that we already have total APR fee
calculated. So only what we need to do
is to post and then
that's it. We can look into our excise
journals again. But to remind you I
mentioned previously you need to choose
the type. Previously we use CBM as a
type. Now we will use EPR as a type. So
that means you need to have created
batch for both CBM and EPR different
batch. You can have more of them but
minimum you need to have one per them.
There are third type is excise but
currently for us this is the most
important you can choose CBM and EPR. So
once when you choose EPR batch you will
confirm and uh you need to use calculate
again you will be asked if you want yes
we want and we will get only one line
because we have only one line in the
sales document.
So what is important now as a uh source
type we are using uh sales invoice and
then we have EPR information ready for
reporting. If you look to our items you
can see items and material composition
source. So this is important. You can go
deeper. So if you choose you can locate
your material composition even you can
look into details. Now this is
composition we material composition we
create recently. So that's it. Let's
close and register this journal excise
journal line. So once when we register
that's okay
we can switch and try to find
transaction logs
excise transaction logs and once when we
have there you can see we have
previously used CBAM entries but this
one entry is marked as a EPR and as a
source there is sales and now you can go
further and find all this information
about EPR calculations CBN calculations
there. So there are uh CBM APR both of
them they are compliance topic
uh not something that probably all of us
like and enjoy to work with but this is
something what is really mandatory by
many regulations especially European
Union. So this is good you can automate
if you set up properly it will help you
a lot in uh future work.
So before we close this session I will
remind you to watch general business
center resources.
There are six different links. It can
help a lot. Then do not forget to
subscribe to LinkedIn page. You can
follow all our weekly news and other
announcements about Business Central and
watch YouTube channel. This video and
other videos related to sustainability
or other topics in this editions are
there or previous editions. So you can
find hundreds of different videos akamsc
YouTube. Thank you for watching this
video.